Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the heavy metal verse. Today we're
going to talk about gold and we're going
to provide an update for the path for
2026. If you guys like the content, make
sure you subscribe to the channel, give
the video a thumbs up, and also check
out the sale on ITC Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
And again, we have the ITC conference
coming up here in just a few months. So,
make sure you guys get your ticket for
that uh in Miami November 21st. Let's go
ahead and jump in. So, gold has
rebounded slightly here off of the lows.
And one of the things about gold that we
should be aware of is that, you know,
while there is certainly a lot of fear
and and and FUD on the timeline about
this this drop in gold, we should be
aware that in gold bull markets, you
will often come back to the 20month
simple moving average or 21-month EMA.
You'll see that in prior gold bull
markets, we will often test that level.
You can see that happened in the 2000s.
It also happened a number of times
throughout the 1970s. And even in that
case, in both of those periods, there
was a region here in that bull market
where gold even dropped below its bull
market support band. Now, remember for
gold and the bull market support band,
we're using the 20month moving average
and the 21-month EMA, not SMAs.
Remember, the price action in
commodities is not nearly as um it
doesn't move nearly as quickly as what
you might see in crypto or in stocks.
And so, I I think it makes sense to look
at some of the longer term moving
averages and and go from there. So when
I look at at these charts, I mean, I I
always have to be cognizant of the fact
that I could be wrong, right? Like it's
always possible that the top the macro
top for the next 20 years is in for
gold, but I don't think it is. When you
look at the year-to- date ROI of gold in
2026,
if you were to overlay that with say
2022,
it's basically doing what it did in
2022. The only difference is that in the
early part of the year, gold went up a
little bit more, but year-to- date, as
measured in 2026 compared to where we
were in 2022, we're actually slightly
underperforming 2022.
But it looks pretty similar. If you look
at 2018 instead of 2022, you'll see that
gold is also basically trading where it
was trading at year to date in 2022. The
only difference is that the initial
upside was a lot more. Now, you could go
back even further and look at some of
the other times and and in 2014, we
ended up going down. It took it took
until November to find the low. uh but
it was a basically where we are now or
where we've been. And so what you could
do is you could say well in 2022 and
gold found a little bit of relief in one
of those years around this time but
there was one more sort of period of
weakness that occurred a little bit
later in the year. When you look at the
average though of all prior midterm
years on average gold bottoms in early
July of midterm years. So what I would
argue is that gold in midterm years, the
main bottoming window is arguably say
June through October, right? June
through October seems like when that
main bottoming window is for gold. And
so while it's possible that I'm wrong
and and that the macro global top for
gold is in for a long time,
it's also completely plausible that the
weakness we've seen in gold is normal
weakness that we often see
in midterm years. As measured from the
high, gold corrected about 30%. If you
look at some of the corrections in prior
bull markets, you can see we had 20 to
30% drops and it did not mean
necessarily that the bull market was
over. So for me, I can't turn bearish on
gold right now. I think that it it spent
so long, you know, consolidating
just around 2000. And this is sort of
your initial move beyond that level. I
think you're going to see at least a
bounce coming in the notsodistant
future. Now, when you look at the
year-to- date ROI, you could argue, all
right, well, you know, either the low is
in or it's really close to being in,
especially when you compare to 2022 or
2018. I'm not really sure if you're
going to get one more drop by gold. If
you do, I would expect it to frontr run
the drop in stocks and probably bottom
sooner than a potential stock
correction, but I don't really see that
correction in stocks even starting until
probably sometime in late September. So,
you know, that's something to consider.
If there is a correction, I I think and
it doesn't even have to be a lower low,
could be a higher low. Um, it would
probably be on the back of the dollar
going higher. So if you look at the
Dixie, you know, it's had a bit of a
correction recently. Obviously, you're
getting risk assets rallying on that,
but I would argue that 2026, gold in
2026 is likely looking or sorry, the
dollar in 2026 looks a lot like the
dollar in 2018 where it just kind of
begrudgingly goes higher. In fact, if
you were to look at the return path of
gold in 2025 or sorry through Donald
Trump's current term and compare it to
Biden's term and Donald Trump's first
term, in both of those cases, this is
the period where gold was in fact weak
in that second year of their of their
office. And then in the third and fourth
years, you can see that gold picked back
up.
So
yes, you could argue maybe we just front
ran things, but I think geopolitical
uncertainty will increase. Um, yeah,
yes, the the the weakness might still be
there for a little bit longer. There
could be that residual weakness that the
dollar moves up. And one of the reasons
you could argue for that is if you look
at the dollar in the current term of
Trump compared to his first term, it
actually looks remarkably similar,
right? it it fell in the first year. It
went sideways. It's now been
begrudgingly moving higher. And so if
that were to continue, if you were to
get one more move up in the dollar um
you know, starting in like a month or
two, that could correspond to that
weakness in gold. But I mean, it could
be a higher low, could be a lower low.
It's hard to say for sure, but I would
argue that if the bull market's intact,
which I still think it is, not financial
advice, I still think it is, then the
June to October time frame is when you
would expect a bottom to occur. And you
know, we haven't even tagged the bull
market support band. There's no
guarantee that we do. I mean, there are
plenty of times where gold does not tag
it before just continuing to move
higher. So, I still think gold looks
fine long term. I I think that, you
know, it's it's going through a massive
consolidation period in 2026. We said to
expect this back in 2025. There was also
a massive consolidation period in 2022
as well. So, we had a move up and then a
consolidation, another move up, and then
a consolidation. And so the argument is
that I think you'll get one final move
up that kind of like ends the decade as
we go into the end of the decade and
then that potentially could end up
actually marking a more global top for
for a while. Those are my views on gold.
Um we'll see if it if it if it plays out
or not, but that is how I expect this
thing to go. And what's interesting is
when you do look at the year-to- date
ROI gold, it is remarkably track
tracking, you know, what it did in 2022,
right? I mean, it bounced around the
same time. If it continues to play out,
it could keep going up into mid August,
maybe get one more period of weakness
before getting back in business. And you
know, when you look at I mean, this is
what it did in 2022 compared to 2026.
But then if you pull up what it did in
2023 and 2024, gold, you know, and 2025,
you know, gold was really moving up
again. Um, or if you go back and look at
the cycle before, right? 2018 was a bad
year. 2019 was moving up. 2020 also
moving up. 2021 slightly slightly down.
But you'll see that those years after
the midterm years
tend to be bullish. If you were to look
at the average of prior pre-election
years for gold, you can see what I'm
talking about. How on average gold goes
up about 13% or so through the
pre-election year, which would be next
year. So again, I think gold will is is
trying to carve out that bottom
and and you know, use that as support to
go higher as we get into later this year
and or you know, going into 2027. Those
are my views. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
make sure you check out the upcoming ITC
conference. We'll obviously be talking
about gold as well. At this conference,
we're going to be talking about a lot of
the major asset classes and, you know,
positioning in these different asset
classes. And hopefully, you guys will
take a lot away from it. Thank you guys
for tuning in and I'll see you next
time. Bye.